{"tossups": [{"question": "A central event in the formation of this group was the adoption of the Great Law of Peace. This group agreed to a series of treaties with the British collectively called the Covenant Chain, and this group fought against the French over control of the fur trade in the Beaver Wars. The Tuscarora joined this group in 1722, leading this group to adopt the nickname the Six Nations. Hiawatha was a leader of, for the point, what confederacy of northeastern Native American tribes?", "answer": "<b> Iroquois</b> Confederacy (or<b> Iroquois</b> League; accept<b> Five Nations</b> and<b> Six Nations</b> before\u201cSix Nations\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s admiral Piri Reis captured the Portuguese outposts of Muscat and Aden. Another of this man\u2019s admirals, Hayreddin Barbarossa, docked in Toulon thanks to his alliance with Francis I of France. This man conquered much of Hungary after the Battle of Moh\u00b4acs [moh-hotch]. Though this ruler oversaw a failed Siege of Malta against the Knights Hospitaller and failed to capture Vienna in 1526, he expanded his empire to its greatest extent. For the point, name this Ottoman ruler, known as \u201cthe Magnificent.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Suleiman</b> the Magnificent (or<b> Suleiman</b> I)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Beveridge curves are used to model this concept, and an empirical relationship between this quantity and a country\u2019s GDP is given by Okun\u2019s law. An \u201cinflation barrier\u201d prevents the full eradication of this economic concept, a theory that developed after stagflation in the 1970s combined inflation and this phenomenon. The negative effects of this concept were dealt with historically by the English Poor Laws. For the point, name this economic phenomenon in which people are unable to find work.", "answer": "<b> unemployment</b> rate (accept descriptive answers relating to<b> job vacancy</b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {}, {"question": "Mao Zedong\u2019s mausoleum is found in this location, which also includes his portrait adorning a large gate. For the point, name this public square where, in 1989, a lone man repeatedly blocked a column of tanks in Beijing.", "answer": "<b> Tiananmen Square</b> (prompt on Beijing before mentioned) Page 1", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A man who served in this position under Jefferson and Madison moved from his estate of Friendship Hill to New York City when he became the first president of NYU. This cabinet position was held from 1801 to 1814 by Albert Gallatin. The first holder of this position drafted the Report on Manufactures and lobbied for a tax on whiskey to help pay down the national debt. The US Mint is overseen by, for the point, what cabinet position first held by Alexander Hamilton?", "answer": "Secretary of the<b> Treasury</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This colony\u2019s government once defrauded natives of all the land a runner could reach in 36 hours, a treaty that became known as \u201cthe Walking Purchase.\u201d This colony, which was regulated by a \u201ccharter of privileges,\u201d purchased much of its land in treaties with the Lenape tribe. To pay a debt owed to the founder\u2019s father, Charles II granted the royal charter creating this colony, whose name means \u201cforest land.\u201d For the point, name this colony, founded as a refuge for Quakers, whose cities included Philadelphia.", "answer": "<b> Pennsylvania</b> (Colony or Province)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The philosopher Thomas Bradwardine held this position for two months shortly before his death. A holder of this position fled to France after he was condemned at a trial held at Northampton Castle, prior to which he had refused to sign the Constitutions of Clarendon. Stephen Langton feuded with King John while he held this position. In 1170, King Henry II ordered the murder of the holder of this position. For the point, name this English religious position held by Thomas Becket.", "answer": "<b> Archbishop of Canterbury</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this country, the Berkut police force was disbanded after a violent suppression of the \u201cHeavenly Hundred\u201d protesters. Minor skirmishes continue to plague this country\u2019s region of Donbass. This country\u2019s Independence Square was the site of the Euromaidan protests, part of a 2014 revolution that ousted Viktor Yanukovych. During the ensuing instability, this country had a Black Sea territory annexed by Vladimir Putin. For the point, name this country that lost the Crimea to neighboring Russia and is governed from Kiev.", "answer": "<b> Ukraine</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In its effort to fight this disease, the NFIP built a facility to mass produce HeLa cells. Albert Sabin developed both an oral vaccine for this disease and an intense rivalry with another vaccine inventor, who asked \u201cCould you patent the sun?\u201d to explain why he didn\u2019t seek profits. The March of Dimes was founded to fight this disease in 1938. Jonas Salk developed a vaccine for, for the point, what mostly eradicated disease that causes muscle weakness and afflicted Franklin Roosevelt?", "answer": "<b> polio</b>myelitis", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "This world leader adopted the Sinatra Doctrine, allowing allied nations to \u201cchoose their own way.\u201dThis leader faced a coup from the hardline Gang of Eight, though it was thwarted when Boris Yeltsin gave a speech from atop a tank. This man\u2019s reforming policies of<em> glasnost</em> and<em> perestroika</em> helped speed up the breakup of his country. For the point, name this final leader of the Soviet Union.", "answer": "Mikhail<b> Gorbachev</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This novel\u2019s author described it as \u201cneither an accusation nor a confession.\u201d In this novel, Tjaden [t\u2019yah-den] gets revenge on Himmelstoss, and another character feels remorse at the stabbing of G\u00b4erard Duval, having returned to the army from seventeen days of leave to see his family. As Fredrich M\u00a8uller dies, he gives Kemmerich\u2019s boots to this novel\u2019s protagonist, Paul Ba\u00a8umer [boy-mar]. For the point, name this Erich Maria Remarque novel about life in the German trenches of World War I.", "answer": "<b> All Quiet on the Western Front</b> (accept<b> Im Westen nichts Neues</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "During this war, the CIA tortured and killed insurgents in the Phoenix Program. Creighton Abrams replaced William Westmoreland as general in this war, in which \u201ctunnel rats\u201d fought in caves and navy pilot John McCain participated in bombing runs during Operation Rolling Thunder. Chemical weapons like Agent Orange were used in, for the point, what Southeast Asian war that ended with Saigon being renamed Ho Chi Minh City?", "answer": "<b> Vietnam</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "For the point, name this US president who pardoned his predecessor, Richard Nixon.", "answer": "Gerald Rudolph<b> Ford</b> Jr. (accept Leslie Lynch<b> King</b>, Jr.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city was home to a lower-class district known as the Subura. Soldiers raised in this city were trained on a large field known as the Campus Martius, and its Temple of Janus only opened its doors in times of war. This city\u2019s sewer, the Cloaca Maxima, drained a swamp that became the site of the first forum. This city was situated on seven hills and was legendarily founded by Romulus and Remus. For the point, name this city on the Tiber River, the namesake of an Italian empire.", "answer": "<b> Rome</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "A leader of this country established its Opportunities assistance program and sharply devalued its currency when he became president in December 1994. Factories called<em> maquiladoras</em> [mah-kee-lah-dor-uhs] were established in this country during the rule of president Ernesto Zedillo. A rebel in this country adopted the name Subcomandante Marcos and began the Zapatista insurgency in 1994. For the point, name this country that is a member of NAFTA with its two northern neighbors.", "answer": "<b> Mexico</b> (or the<b> United Mexican States</b> or<b> Estados Unidos Mexicanos</b>) Page 5", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Joseph-Marie Jacquard names a type of this material with complex designs, as well as the machine used for producing it. Another highly decorative type of this material, often using floral patterns, is named for Damascus. Lowell was the site of several strikes of primarily female workers in this industry. For the point, name this kind of material often produced by weaving the fibers from linen or wool.", "answer": "<b> cloth</b> or<b> fabric</b> or<b> textile</b>s (accept<b> clothing</b>; prompt on cotton, linen, wool or other specific fibers used in the industry) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "An early offensive in this battle was Joseph Hooker\u2019s assault on the Dunker Church, which led to heavy fighting in Miller\u2019s Cornfield. A Union objective in the southern part of this battle was nicknamed Burnside\u2019s Bridge. Fighting over the Sunken Road led to a stalemate in this battle, which was followed by Robert Lee\u2019s withdrawal of the Confederate army from Maryland. For the point, name this Civil War battle with the highest one-day death toll in American history.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Antietam</b> (accept Battle of<b> Sharpsburg</b>) Page 6", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}